hi everyone I'm jakub and uh today I'll
um I'm going to give a very brief
overview of uh some
projects that we've been developing at
the Active inference Institute and
their relevance to to decentralized AI
now I think my uh talk and Alex is right
after me is going to overlap slightly so
uh
I'm going to try to keep the theory of
active inference and one particular
project to
um a minimum although I'll try to give
some brief
um brief introduction to what active
inference is so that you uh have the
relevant background so since this is a
mini conference on decentralized AI I'm
going to assume that
um most of you have at least heard of
reinforcement learning which on the
computational side is quite similar to
active inference but we can think of
active inference as being a kind of
generalization of reinforcement learning
where agents uh interact with their
environment or and try to solve a
certain task or try to navigate in their
environment but instead of
um maximizing some utility function or
uh instead of their goal being always
maximizing for reward
um active inference agents are perhaps
more General where the kind of utility
function or the general function of
active inference agents is always
uncertainty minimization so active
inference agents form some kind of
internal model of their environment and
they can learn more about their
environment by engaging with it through
action and then
um
observing what uh what kind of uh sense
sensory input goes from the environment
to the agents so there's a kind of
Duality between perception and action
that's always mediated through
uncertainty minimization and uh
because of its generality this framework
can be applied to pretty much any system
that's
um Salient enough to persist through
time which was
kind of the motivation for uh the first
project
which Alex will talk about a bit more so
I'm only going to mention it briefly
which is the active entity ontology for
science uh which really stands at the
intersection of three Fields namely DSi
systems engineering and active inference
where our aim was to create an ontology
that individuals and communities within
DSi can use to collectively minimize
their uncertainty about what uh kind of
system they find themselves in and how
that system might evolve through time
and
I think this is uh the same can be done
for decentralized AI which has a lot of
uh similar artifacts that have to do
with web3 and
um perhaps we can say that either DSi is
encapsulated within decentralized AI or
the other way around depending on uh
which you think is the bigger uh bigger
set but the core
um
the core utility of having a shared
ontology that's kind of grounded in
another formal framework namely active
inference allows us to
more
um specifically Define what kind of
entities and artifacts we can find in a
system and
how um how these entities interact with
each other
and minimize their minimize their
uncertainty uh so we can kind of have a
better understanding of the Dynamics of
our system and be able to better
um make decisions about what kind of
protocols we should create or how should
our uh community
interact with other communities and
uh and so on this also uh leads me to uh
the active blog friends project which
aims which is kind of on the
computational side of EOS where we aim
to uh combine
um the open source framework CAD CAD
which was developed by block science and
that's been used uh mainly for token
engineering and also just generalized
dynamical systems modeling
um where you usually take a kind of
structural top-down approach to modeling
uh your system of inner interest where
you define your state space and then you
perform giant parameter sweeps to try to
figure out uh how your state space
evolves through time and what kind of
edge cases can you
um can you get to and combining that
with active inference cognitive modeling
where you have agents that have kind of
emergent properties
that through Collective infra
interaction form these
um
uh communities that themselves can be
can be cast as agents within some
environment so you have this
um bottom uh bottom-up emergent Behavior
through agent agents interacting and
trying to minimize their uncertainty as
well as
um a kind of top-down parameter sweep
over all the possible States in your
system
um this might sound a little abstract
but I think
um it's quite relevant for decentralized
AI and
mainly for two different reasons one of
them is
we uh we want to create different
communities and protocols for both uh
co-owning or creating AI models or
interacting with AI models and
that's already a quite
um quite large State space so it would
be help it would definitely be about AI
alignment which is
also a very big question in a big
problem in in AI where
you're basically trying to align
uncertainty minimization across
different types of Agents as well as
um different levels of your system where
doubt want to minimize their uncertainty
with respect to other doubts or with
respect to
um some uh some preset goal but
individuals within those doubts also
need to uh
minimize their uncertainty based on
their own preferences which may or may
not align with those of
um
of the higher level system and the same
can be said of
um of AI models and autonomous agents
which are deaf which are definitely
becoming more
um more present in the in the digital
space
um
so that would be a very uh brief
overview of some of the projects that
were developing at the Active inference
Institute and
uh if you have any questions then
um
I'm not sure whether we have the time
but thanks a lot for your for your
attention
yeah you have a couple you have about a
minute so
um maybe we'll save them for a little
bit later unless they're quite quick
okay I'm not seeing any text questions
yet so um I'll definitely invite people
to ask you any questions that they have
about that either in the 10 minute
session or towards the end when we
finish
um we've got about a minute now so I
will thank you very much for that very
cool to hear what you're doing I'll
bring up your your colleague uh now
hi Alex how are you
yeah fine thanks hi everyone cool take
it away
okay
can you see it right
so I will add here some information
about active inference and a a a EOS and
continue to Jacob talk but also will
provide more information from Institute
scale about our work and possible
collaboration service our participants
so
we are Institute which is working on
Frontier or effective inference as we
consider it and it's a scale free
cognitive framework which is based based
on first principles but models decision
making processes and actions of actions
in the environment
and it's quite important about scale
free here because it means that we can
apply it for different types of Agents
and systems and for me personally very
important that which but it's based on
first principles starting from from
physics
from thermodynamics from
information Theory to Quantum
information Theory it's quite broad
space for people who are like math and
physics
this framework combines perception
actions and inference inference
so
optimize information processing and
handle uncertainty
in relation to different kinds of Agents
it can be polite which was mentioned for
robotics for artificial intelligence but
also a lot our fields and domains like
neuroscience and with for now we see
real world examples of application of
the framework
active inference agent acting to
minimize his surprises in informational
sense and maximize maximize expected
outcomes on different time scales
having his generative model in place and
updating it or updating environment
uh this process
always based on gathering information
and based on it generating actions
based on that generative probabilistic
models
as I mentioned it could be applied for
various fields and we are as Institute
starting it from ourselves in the
beginning from Team Communications
and later receive Buffs to decision
making management governance and a lot
of other
things related to organizations as
entities and as as agents
as for
active entity ontology for science first
of all
we could see in terms of active
inference we can consider it as a part
of a shared General generative model
of people's personalities or
organizations or projects which should
have some common language in place
and having it
there are some
Evolution happening and providing ways
to structure to
represent different scientific
knowledges in a common way to enable
efficient collaborations and knowledge
sharing
it can facilitate interoperability
across different scientific domains
standardized concept and relationships
and finally it could be a way to
accelerate scientific discoveries
and Inter inter interdisciplinary
collaborations
you can find some additional information
and to actually paper by with links and
the ontology as itself you can find on
coder page
maybe have a look and consider if it's
connects
with you in some way and important here
that
how it could be developed both active
inference as a framework as a
Cornerstone and in developments with
active inference
can improve decision making and
collaboration of teams of organizations
there are possible ways and different
ways to integrate it with blockchain
standards
which enhanced
digitalizations of such scientific
artifacts
which later
in evolutionary manner could be
reproduced and evolved
for all different communities
finally we consider
Institute as a part of research
ecosystem
and our intentions here to provide
we as an agent
to provide more interfaces and more
structured ways to communicate in this
Frontier domains because it's quite hard
science
and we need to find ways to
use common language in different
projects and by that
of all evolve research existence
so I think
that's all from from my site
so if you have some questions
can you hear me
nice way
yeah we can we'll give it a few minutes
maybe if people want to type some
questions okay
really cool stuff it's incredible how
complex and I can see a lot of different
ways that you could collaborate with
people in many many different fields so
it's very cool
cool thank you